בוקר טוב *Boker tov*, חברה *chevra*. בוקר טוב *Boker tov*, חודש טוב
*chodesh tov*. We are on דף daf ט"ו *Daf Tes-Vav*, 15. We're
picking up at the bottom of י"ד עמוד ב' *Yod-Dalet
amud beis*, and where it says אמר אביי Amar Abaye, תא שמע
tah shema, *Amar Abaye ta shma*. It is three, six, eight lines
before the lines get wide, about 13 lines from the bottom, line
starts with the word לדיני דכתבו ליה *le-dinei de-katvu lei*. אמר אביי
Abaye, *Amar Abaye*. So the discussion at hand is the משנה mishna.
*Mishna* introduced not shaving and getting your haircut and laundry on חול
המועד Chol HaMoed *Chol HaMoed*, with the exceptions of people who had
no option beforehand—freed from prison, came back from an overseas journey,
a נזיר *Nazir* or מצורע metzora *Metzora* that were becoming טהור *tahor*,
a person who was in נידוי niddui *Nidui* in a type of
a minor form of excommunication who was then had that released and
therefore was allowed to get a haircut now and to bathe and
to launder his clothes now. Now, so that's—so this is really introducing
us, this פרק *Perek* in particular, besides it's going to be a
transition to הלכות Halachos אבילות aveilus *Hilchos Aveilus*, really introduces us to,
you know, to putting some different types of categories alongside one another
and really thinking seriously about them. So number one, the fact that
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* had to find a special reason why these
things normally were not allowed on חול המועד Chol HaMoed *Chol HaMoed*
and said in order to ensure that people come into יום טוב
Yom Tov, *Yom Tov*, you know, with their clothes laundered and their
haircut and so on, we're going to make it forbidden on יום
טוב Yom Tov, *Yom Tov* to make sure you take care of
it ahead of time, and why the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* didn't just
give the reason that it's a מלאכה melacha, *melacha*. So that raises
questions about what exactly constitutes מלאכה melacha, *melacha* on חול המועד Chol
HaMoed. *Chol HaMoed* and as we pointed out yesterday, very little evidence
in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that it is anything to do with
the idea of like the 39 מלאכות *melachos*, although תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos*
keeps on trying to bring that in. The phrase the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* more uses is טרחה *tircha*, effort, although not all the things
in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* were so much what we would sort
of put under a טרחה *tircha* category. You might really try to
say that it's more of somewhat of an amorphous idea of sort
of like weekday activity and what constitutes that and therefore things like
working the fields and business and commerce are things that particularly were
highlighted. So it's possible that even though cutting your hair and doing
laundry is classic ל"ט מלאכות lamed tes melachos? *Lamed-Tes Melachos*, the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* needed a special reason why those weren't allowed on חול
המועד Chol HaMoed *Chol HaMoed* and that's always an interesting question even
to today in practical הלכה *halacha*. If somebody actually does one of
these things without the allowances, are we saying that they're violating a
מלאכה melacha *melacha* on חול המועד Chol HaMoed. *Chol HaMoed*, or do
we say that they just went against the rabbinic ruling that you
need to take care of it ahead of time so you don't,
you know, you can't do it on חול המועד Chol HaMoed. *Chol
HaMoed* in order to ensure you take care of it ahead of
time. How do you think about these two things? So that's one
issue. The other issue though is as we're beginning to see that
ironically these things are the exact same type of practices that we
normally encounter in times of mourning. So an אבל avel *avel* doesn't
do these things, a somebody who's in נידוי niddui. *Nidui*, which is
what we're about to explore, or a מצורע metzora *Metzora*—now that's not
exactly about mourning but obviously it's about a type of a sort
of, you know, a being a pushed out of society, very different
type of an experience than שמחת הרגל simchat ha-regel *Simchas HaRegel*. So
on the one hand you have that irony, and on the other
hand, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* yesterday introduced the idea and what we're
sort of dealing with right now is to what degree does שמחת
הרגל *Simchas HaRegel* override practices of mourning, override practices of נידוי niddui,
*Nidui*, override the practices of מצורע metzora *Metzora*, and very logically puts
those two realms into
opposition. So what we looked at yesterday was the idea that אבילות
aveilus *aveilus* is not practiced during the רגל regel *regel*, as we
know if somebody's in אבילות aveilus *aveilus*, the רגל regel *regel* actually
ends that period of אבילות aveilus? *aveilus*, and the question the גמרא
Gemara: *Gemara* is immediately attending to right now is does אבילות aveilut
*aveilus* override somebody who is in a state of נידוי niddui. *Nidui*,
who is in a state of being somewhat like
excommunicated—again I grapple for a better word because the real excommunicated is
חרם cherem, *cherem*, but נידוי niddui *Nidui* is sort of like castigated,
maybe that's a better word, by the rabbinic authorities, often as we
found out yesterday it was a way of, it was a mild
form of sort of like coercion or of, you know, of trying
to sort of get people to abide by you know either a
form of like punishment or to get compliance to sort of like
rabbinic standards and rules and so on and the בית דין *Beis
Din* etc. and one of the practices is, you know, somebody in
that state doesn't do his laundry, doesn't cut his hair, etc., etc.,
similar to sort of experiences of אבילות aveilut. *aveilus*. And the question
is is during the רגל regel, *regel* do those things continue to
be practiced or not? We just said that by אבילות aveilut *aveilus*
רגל regel *regel* overrides, what about somebody in a state of נידוי
niddui *Nidui*? And that's what we're turning to now. You had a
question, Avery?
Two questions. Number one is that it sounds like the rationale that
you have for not cutting your hair and not doing laundry on
יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov* is exactly the antithesis of what
you're doing for—correct. But if that's—but if the purpose then and if
where our
power...
Well, that's what the גמרא Gemara says, yeah.
Okay, so you'll properly prepare, then why not state it in a
positive way?
How could you say
why do you require people to do it?
Yeah, you require them to prepare in advance of the חג chag
and say you should...
Yeah, that requirement is sort of already on the books. You know,
we already have גמרות Gemaras that talk about doing things for כבוד
שבת Kovod Shabbos and כבוד יום טוב Kovod Yom Tov and so
on.
I think the feeling is, and this is something that we've seen
before, מכוין מלאכתו במועד, Mechavin Melachto B'Moed, that if people are off
of work on חול המועד Chol HaMoed but technically can do מלאכה,
melacha. it's not שבת Shabbos and it's not יום טוב, Yom Tov,
but they're not doing... if they're following what we've been learning in
this מסכת, masechet, they're not going to their job. So there's a
concern that people will actually say, oh, let's just wait till חול
המועד Chol HaMoed. and we'll take care of all this business. So
I think that therefore they felt a particular need to like make
certain, you know, safeguards so that people don't postpone things to חול
המועד. Chol HaMoed. But anyway, my basic answer is yeah, there are
ideas on the... you know, there is an idea of כבוד יום
טוב Kovod Yom Tov and כבוד שבת Kovod Shabbos that's there. So
I think the question is not why didn't they say it in
the positive, but why do they need an added incentive? Why isn't
it enough? They don't tell you don't do certain things on שבת
Shabbos to make sure you take care of כבוד שבת, Kovod Shabbos,
and you would think רגל regel. is even more of a big
deal; it comes less frequently in the year. So I think that
at least what I would say the answer to that is the
earlier גמרא Gemara about
מכוין מלאכתו במועד. Mechavin Melachto B'Moed. That you have this whole period,
you have a week in which on the one hand it's not
strictly אסור במלאכה, assur b'melacha, right, whatever it is, it's like a
more vague category, and you're not going to work, so you might
דווקא davka want to postpone certain things to that time. But anyway,
I mean that's as far... that's the answer I can give. If
you're open to other suggestions. Yes, Charlie?
Koren translates נידוי niddui as ostracism.
Ostracism. Okay, that's better than excommunication. That's a good middle word. Okay,
so moving on, let's take a look. So that's the גמרא's Gemara,
question about רגל regel. and נידוי. niddui So let's take a look.
אמר אביי, Abaye says אביי, Abaye תא שמע, ta shma come and
hear from our משנה. mishna. ומנודה שהתירו לו חכמים, Umenudeh sheheetiru lo
chachamim, that one person who can get a haircut and launder clothes
on חול המועד Chol HaMoed. is a מנודה, menudeh, somebody who has
a נידוי, niddui, ostracized, that was released. Now אביי Abaye reads that
not that he was proactively released, but that automatically because it's the
רגל, regel. became released, is free now, so that רגל regel. does
not apply during the רגל. regel So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so
רבא Rava said back to him, that's not what it means. מקתני
שהתירוהו חכמים, Miktani sheheetiruhoo chachamim, it doesn't say that the חכמים chachamim
allowed such a person as a general thing on the רגל. regel
אלא
שהתירו לו חכמים, Ella sheheetiru lo chachamim, that the חכמים chachamim like
made it permissible for him. Now again, the difference שהתירוהו sheheetiruhoo and
שהתירו לו חכמים, sheheetiru lo chachamim, but the לו lo makes it,
you know, seem a little more specific. In your case, you were
freed from it on the... on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. It's not
a general thing that people are freed from these practices on חול
המועד. Chol HaMoed תני דאזל ופייסיה לבעל דיניה, Tani de'azal u'faysay l'baal
dineh,
what he went is he went and he appeased the person he
was having a debate with—not a debate, you know, a fight with—ואתי
קמי דרבנן ושרו ליה, ve'asi kamei d'rabbanan u'sharo leh,
and then he came to the rabbis and the rabbis, you know,
permitted him, meaning removed his state of נידוי. niddui So maybe they
put him in a state of נידוי niddui because he wasn't complying
to a certain judgment or because, you know, some other type of
a conflict that they found him at fault for. And he resolved
it and then the rabbis released him from this state. That's the
פשט pshat of the משנה. mishna But the basic פשט pshat of
the משנה Mishnah, is the opposite of what אביי said, is that
if it were not for that special case, he would be still
observing his state of נידוי niddui, during the... during the רגל. regel.
And the גמרא Gemara, does not really have a conclusion, but the
simple evidence is according to רבא Rava that נידוי nidui does apply
during the רגל. regel Now תוספות Tosafos asks the question, why does
נידוי niduy. apply during the רגל regel. if אבילות aveilut does not?
And תוספות' Tosafos suggestion is that well, אבילות aveilut does not, the
גמרא Gemara says because רגל regel, is שמחה דרבים simcha de'rabbim and
that overrides אבילות דיחיד. aveilus de'yachid. So תוספות Tosafos says the state
of נידוי, niddui although practiced as a יחיד, yachid, might be considered
to be a concern of the רבים. rabbim. Because if this is
how the rabbis sort of, you know, control society, or one of
their strategies of controlling society, so people practicing their נידוי niddui, is
a type of a concern of the רבים, rabbim, and therefore it
might continue to apply during the רגל. regel I would suggest something
else, which is, and this is something that because what we're going
to be focused on mostly today is the list of practices that
an אבל avel does, the list of practices that a מצורע metzora.
does, and the list of practices that somebody in נידוי does. And
they're going to be mostly the same, but the list of אבילות
aveilut practices is going to be longer. There's going to be some
areas where an אבל avel does that are not done by the
others. And the real question is, right, how do you understand the
status of a מצורע metzora, and somebody in נידוי, and why are
those practices similar to אבילות? aveilut I mean, they're not in mourning.
So what are their practices about? And I would suggest, and we'll
continue to talk about this as we continue today, that their practices
are much more about being sort of like, I think ostracized was
a good word, outside and ostracized from society. Like the מצורע metzora.
is מחוץ למחנה. michutz lamachaneh. I'm not going to get into the
whole issue about לשון הרע *lashon hara* or whatever reasons we give,
but nonetheless, the reality is Torah clearly says the מצורע metzora. *Metzoira*
is cast out of society because בגדיו יהיו פרמים וראשו יהיה פרוע
V'rosho yihye parua, *bigdav yihyu frumim v'rosho yihye parua*, טמא tamei, טמא
tamei יקרא *tamei tamei yikra*. Clearly, the image one has is stay
away, stay away, and the way he appears is one that sort
of says I am not fit for normal society. My clothes are
rent, my hair is wild. So this person is cast out of
society and the same about a מנודה menudeh *menudeh*. The what נידוי
*niddui* was was the effect of sort of putting this person in
a sort of castigated, quasi-ostracized role until he complied, until his behavior
was more in line what the societal, you know sort of expectations
and demands were, you know, not just sort of society, but whatever,
the the rabbinic expectations about how how people have to live within,
you know, their within that type of a society. So if these
are practices therefore about being outside, now part of אבילות aveilut *aveilus*
practices could be that. Part of אבילות aveilut *aveilus* practices is that
somebody like, you know, they sit שבעה *shiva*. You're not in the
normal flow and rhythms of the world, you are removed in order
to be focusing on, you know, the state on the tragedy and
to be, you know, for a period of נחמה *nechama* and also
for a period of being able to sort of, you know, focus
and grapple and you're not in a state yet to move back
to the normal world. So there is that element. But there's also
just the element of an expression of your your profound sense of
sadness and mourning, which is not relevant to the other two categories.
So with that in mind, it could be that the reason רגל
regel. *Regel* overrides אבילות aveilut *aveilus* than it does these other two
categories is because רגל regel. *Regel* and אבילות Avelus, *aveilus* are very
much antithetical. רגל regel, *Regel* is שמחה simchah *simcha* and אבילות Avelus,
*aveilus* is sadness. So therefore, there is going to be a direct
conflict, where these other two people, even if having my hair grow
wild and my clothes rent or whatever doesn't allow me to participate
in שמחת הרגל *simchas haregel* to the same degree, they're not an
expression of sadness. By the מצורע metzora *Metzoira* and the מנודה Menudeh
*menudeh*, they're an expression of ostracism, they're not an expression of sadness.
So therefore, the רגל regel *Regel*'s ability to override is less because
it's operating on a different plane. The רגל regel *Regel* says you
have to be שמח *sameach*. This is not saying I'm not שמח
*sameach*, it's just saying something else, ostracized from society. The harder it
is for me to be שמח *sameach*, but it's not about a
antithetical expression to what the רגל regel *Regel* is. So that's why
I believe that these things are practiced on the רגל regel, *Regel*,
whereas אבילות Avelus, *aveilus* is not. So we did מנודה Menudeh *menudeh*,
and now we're going to go to מצורע metzora. *Metzoira*. So let's
take a look. Let's just see מצורע metzora *Metzoira*. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* just wants to sort of finish that thought. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: מצורע metzora מהו שינהיג צרעתו ברגל
*Metzoira mahu sheyanhig tzoraso baregel*? How about a מצורע Metzora *Metzoira*, does
he practice his צרעת tzaraat, *tzoraas*? You know, obviously he's טמא tamei.
*tamei*, so the strict sense of טומאה tumah *tumah* applies, but how
about the practices that are unique to a מצורע Metzora *Metzoira*, like
the ones particularly here about hair growing wild and rent garments? That's
a little shocking. You would think it's explicit in the פסוקים Pesukim
*pesukim* that this is what a מצורע Metzora. *Metzoira* does, to think
that, oh okay, but not on the רגל regel *Regel*. I mean,
that's just a shocking הוה אמינא *hava amina*. Let's see what the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. אמר אביי *Amar Abaye*, said אביי *Abaye*, תא
שמע Ta shma, *ta shma*, come and
hear, והנזיר והמצורע מטומאתן לטהרתן *v'hanazir v'hametzoira mitumasan letaharasan*. That who's allowed
to get a haircut and to do their clothes? A נזיר *nazir*
and a מצורע Metzora, *Metzoira* that are becoming טהור *tahor*.
So it sounds because they're טהור *tahor* now, they are now able
to cut their hair and, you know, do their clothes, whatever, by
מצורע Metzora? *Metzoira*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: הא בימי טומאתו
לא *ha b'imei tumaso lo*. So you see that when a מצורע
Metzora. *Metzoira* is טמא *tamei*, he can't do these types of things,
even if it were the רגל regel *Regel*. The only reason he's
allowed during the רגל regel *Regel* is because he's becoming טהור *tahor*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no: לא צריכא *lo tzricha*. You
could say it goes without saying. לא צריכא בימי טומאתו דלא נהיג
*lo tzricha b'imei tumaso d'lo nahig*, if he was really in the
middle of his טומאה tumah *tumah*, then of course he wouldn't have
to do these things on the רגל regel *Regel*. That's pretty shocking,
okay, because it's the רגל regel *Regel* that overrides. אבל avel לטהרתו
*aval letaharato*, but now that he's טהור *tahor* and he's in the
process of becoming טהור *tahor*, so now you would think certainly he
doesn't have to do it in the רגל regel, *Regel*. No, and
here here's a little bit of what I was saying to you
before: נגזר שמא ישהה קרבנותיו *nigzar shema yishahei korbanosav*, maybe ironically, paradoxically,
if this if this מצורע Metzora *Metzoira* is becoming טהור *tahor*, we
won't let him do these stuff on the רגל *Regel*. Why? I
mean, all the more reason, I'm becoming טהור *tahor*, it's the רגל
*Regel*. Ah, but now you're going to say, look, if I was
טהור *tahor* a week or a month before סוכות *Succos*, I'm not
going to שלעפ *schlepp* all the way to ירושלים *Yerushalayim* a week
before סוכות *Succos*. I'll wait for a week and I'll wait till
it's סוכות *Succos* time and then I'll take care of finishing my
טהרה *tahara* process and bringing my קרבנות korbanot *korbanos* and so on.
So in order to not give me a, you know, incentive or
to not or to block that sort of, the you know, that
temptation to wait for the רגל *Regel* to take care of it
and that I should take care of it right away, there we're
going to say maybe we won't let me do these types of
things on the רגל *Regel*, do my טהרה *tahara* practices on the
רגל *Regel* in order to force me to take care of it
in the time and not to postpone it. קמ"ל *ka mashma lan*
that we're not going to say that, that we're going to let
you go ahead and do these things on the רגל *Regel* and
we're not afraid that it's going to lead to postponement. But there,
David, you see this concern that דוקא there will be reasons to
postpone things during the רגל anyway. So the גמרא Gemara says it's
possible that it would be allowed to override these things about the
hair and so on, you know, even in the middle of the
טומאה Tumah of a מצורע. Metzora But while the גמרא—but Gemara certainly
not the פשט pshat of the משנה, Mishnah, and let's see how
this concludes. אמר רבא Amar Rava says רבא Rava תא שמע Tashma:
come and hear, והצרוע ve-hatzarua and the one who has צרעת, tzaraat?
so that extra phrase, like, you know, it says הצרוע אשר בו
הנגע, ha-tzarua asher bo ha-naga, so the word הצרוע ha-tzarua is extra,
because it could have just said אשר בו הנגע. asher bo ha-naga.
So לרבות כהן גדול, lerabot Kohen Gadol, even a כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol has to practice his practices of a מצורע, Metzora, not just
that he's טמא, but the practices of a מצורע. metzora? And the
גמרא Gemara says a fascinating line in the גמרא: Gemara דכהן גדול
דכל השנה כרגל לכל עלמא דמי. de-Kohen Gadol de-khol ha-shanah ke-regel le-khol
alma dami. A כהן גדול Kohen Gadol during
the—on any day of the year is like a normal person on
the רגל. How do you know that? דתנן, de-tnan, we learn a
משנה, Mishnah. כהן גדול מקריב אונן ואינו אוכל. Kohen Gadol makriv onen
ve-eino okhel. A כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol can bring קרבנות korbanot while he's an אונן, onen,
although he can't eat them, right? So what's the logic of that?
The only logic is that his status of a כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol overrides the reality of an אונן. onen. Now where do we
know that for a normal person something overrides his אונן/אבילות status? The
גמרא Gemara here doesn't distinguish between אנינות aninut and אבילות. Avelus. So
where do we know that for a normal person? We only know
that like we said before on the רגל, that the רגל overrides
the status. So you see a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is like
a רגל. And nevertheless, he practices the practices of a מצורע. metzora
And the גמרא Gemara says שמע מינה, shma mina, that's good evidence.
You see that a מצורע metzora does his practices during the רגל.
Again, quite bizarre, כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is like the רגל, but
it is interesting because this is a point that the רב Rav
makes a lot, which is that the specific idea of like שמחת
הרגל or some of the specific ideas around the רגל are because,
you know, the רגל is about going up and עליה לרגל. aliyah
la-regel. It's about being in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and about
being in the presence of God, right? And when the גמרא, Gemara
for example, says שמחה simchah by רגל אין שמחה אלא בבשר שלמים
ein simchah ela be-vasar shelamim because the eating of the meat, but
it's the meat of the קרבנות and it's sort of that connection
to God conjoined with or connected with the sort of physical pleasure
that comes through the eating of the meat, but that direct sort
of being, you know, in God's presence. So in that sense, saying
that a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol always is seen—right, that's the way
the תורה Torah describes him, right? Like he, you know, he's always—even
if he's physically not in the מקדש, Mikdash, conceptually that's always where
he is. ומן המקדש לא יצא, U-min ha-Mikdash lo yeitzei, right? So
therefore the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is always in that sense of
in the presence of God and whatever שמחה simchah that that entails,
and nevertheless, he does the practices of a מצורע. metzora And therefore
says the גמרא, Gemara the same would be true about a normal
מצורע metzora. would do the practices on the רגל, which certainly is
the פשט pshat of the משנה. Mishnah. So again what you have
is that the simple evidence is that מצורע metzora and מנודה Menudeh,
do their practices on the רגל although an אבל Avel does not.
And I would argue, as I said before, that the reason is
because although these practices get in the way of שמחה—how simchah שמחה
simcha could I be if my hair is disheveled and my clothes
are, you know, are smelly and all these types of things—nevertheless they're
not expressions of אבילות avelus and of sadness. And therefore they—the רגל
does not override, as opposed to אבילות aveilus, where these are expressions
of אבילות aveilut and צער tzaar and sadness and therefore the רגל
overrides those things because the רגל is the antithesis of that. Yes,
David, you had a question?
Okay.
Alright. So that's these things, that what רגל overrides אבילות aveilut. but
does not override these two things. Now we go on to this
core issue, which is implicit in the previous discussion about how these
three categories have very similar practices, but as I've been saying, אבילות
aveilut definitely has more practices because אבילות aveilut, is about something beyond
what those other two categories are about. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says like this. אבל אסור בתספורת. Avel asur be-tisporet. An אבל Avel
can't get a haircut, which is pretty implicit in our משנה. Mishnah
But now we're going to give some of the sourcing of it.
מדקאמר ליה רחמנא לבני אהרן Mi-de-ka-amar lei Rachmana le-vnei Aharon because God
says to the sons of Aaron once, you know, נדב ואביהוא Nadav
ve-Avihu died, ראשיכם אל תפרעו, rosheikhem al tifrau, do not let your
hair grow wild, which means don't get a haircut presumably. מכלל דכולי
עלמא אסור. Mi-klal de-khulei alma asur. And from there you can infer
that they—the גמרא Gemara understands that there God was telling them you
are in special circumstances, so don't do אבילות practices. And from which
we can infer that normal—what normal אבילות practices would have been: to
let the hair grow wild, not to get a haircut.
מנודה ומצורע מה הן בתספורת? Menudeh u-metzora mah hen be-tisporet? How about
somebody in נידוי and צרעת? Tzara'as, Again these two are going to
be always—I mean, they're not always necessarily going to have the same
answer, but we'll see they are very much come together as I
said, I think it's about this sense of ostracization. So what is
their story in terms of getting a haircut? Now already pretty clear
in our משנה Mishnah. they can't get a haircut because those other
ones which, if their status changed on the רגל, they're allowed to
get a haircut on חול המועד chol ha-moed because they couldn't beforehand.
But nevertheless, we're looking for earlier sourcing of it even though it's
implicit in our משנה. Mishna So what's the story about מנודה ומצורע
menudeh u-metzora for getting a haircut? תא שמע, ta shma come and
hear, מנודה ומצורע menudeh u-metzora we have a ברייתא beraita אסורין לספר
ולכבס. asurin le-saper u-lekhabbes. A מנודה Menudeh *menudeh* and מצורע metzora? *metzora*
cannot get a haircut and cannot do laundry, again, pretty implicit in
our משנה Mishna *mishna*. It does not give a source for it.
And then the ברייתא braisa *braita* goes on. מנודה Menudeh שמת *Menudeh
shemeit*, now if a מנודה Menudeh *menudeh* dies in the state of
נידוי *nidui* of ostracized, בית דין סוקלין את ארונו *Beis din soklin
es arono*. The בית דין *beis din* sort of stones his his
coffin. רבי יהודה אומר לא שיעמידו עליו גל אבנים כגלו של עכן
*Rabbi Yehuda omer lo sheya'amidu alav gal avanim k'galo shel Achan*, not
that they would put a pile of stones on him on the
coffin like they did in the story of עכן *Achan* by יהושע
*Yehoshua*, אלא בית דין שולחין ומניחין אבן גדולה על ארונו *ela beis
din sholchin u'menichin even gedola al arono*. They put a big stone,
one single stone, on his ארון *aron*, but basically to say that
this person, you know, never, you know, died still in in a
state of ostracization. Now the idea of סוקלין *soklin* is pretty harsh
because being like סוקלין *soklin* as a sort of a figurative way
of killing the person, right, of executing the person, seems pretty harsher
than just an idea of sort of being ostracized. One just wants
to say like you bury him at the edge of the cemetery
or something like that, you know? So it's it you know, it
really is quite harsh and I can't fully explain it. But anyway,
and this ברייתא braisa. *braita* ends, ללמדך שכל המתנדה ומת בנידויו בית
דין סוקלין את ארונו *Lelamedcha shekol hamitnadeh u'meis b'niduyo beis din soklin
es arono*. It's pretty funny, that's exactly what you just said. But
okay, to teach you that that anybody who dies in that state,
בית דין *beis din* is סוקלין את ארונו *soklin es arono*. So
that's that's just the end of the ברייתא braita *braita*, not exactly,
I mean it's fascinating, but not exactly our topic. But again, we
have a ברייתא braita *braita* that says they don't get a haircut
and they don't laundry, doesn't give a source, although of course by
מצורע metzora, *metzora*, the source of getting a haircut is ראשו יהיה
פרוע Rosho yihye parua, *rosho yihyeh parua*, right? That says explicit by
מצורע metzora *metzora*, although we'll learn in a little bit to apply
that to something slightly different. Now מצורע metzora *metzora* also says the
garments are rent, it doesn't say you don't laundry your garments, in
theory you could laundry your rent garments, but clearly there's a sense
of the disheveled, you know, sort of and and sort of outside
of society, you know, sort of practice in terms of the wearing
of the garments and therefore not laundering the garments goes along with
it. So the source of this by מצורע metzora *metzora* is pretty
clear, we of course we here extend it to מנודה Menudeh *menudeh*
as well, we have this ברייתא braita, *braita*, it's implicit in our
משנה Mishna *mishna*. Yes.
I think this is lenient for the for the person, for the
ostracized person.
Oh, because it's like it signifies like כפרה *kapara*.
Well, well, and also they are letting him be buried in the
Jewish cemetery.
Well, that's true. So maybe that's true. And also maybe it could
be seen as a form of כפרה *kapara* since you didn't take
care of whatever you needed to while you while you were alive.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. So that's that's haircut.
אבל Avel. *Avel*, an אבל avel *avel* is חייב chayav בעטיפת הראש
*chayav b'atifat harosh*, has to wrap the head. This is in obviously
in a society in which they had, you know, like turban, not
just turbans, but you know, sort of like, you know, scarves that
would go over the entire face. And that's what an אבל avel
*avel* would have to do, a veil, essentially enveil his face. מדיקאמר
ליה רחמנא ליחזקאל Rachmana l'Yechezkel, *Mideika'amar lei rachmana l'Yechezkel*, because God says
to יחזקאל Yechezkel, *Yechezkel*, ולא תעטה על שפה *v'lo ta'ateh al safah*,
do not sort of, you know, cover over, you know, wrap a
sort of garment around your around your lips, or מכלל דכולי עלמא
מיחייבי *michlal d'chulei alma michayvei*. So again, so יחזקאל Yechezkel *Yechezkel* was
to do this symbolic אבלות Avelus *aveilus*. What's going to be a
little interesting about יחזקאל Yechezkel *Yechezkel* is that God says to in
the this story about יחזקאל *Yechezkel* is doing this symbolic אבלות Avelus
*aveilus*, you know, to sort of signify that בני ישראל *Bnei Yisrael*
are going to be sent into exile and so on. God says
like don't do a couple of things, do a couple of things,
some of them we're going to assume are the rules for an
אבל avel *avel* and some of them we're going to assume are
the exception, meaning that יחזקאל *Yechezkel* was told to do opposite of
what a normal אבל avel *avel* did. So by some of the
practices of יחזקאל *Yechezkel* we learn that an אבל avel *avel* does
the opposite, and by some of the practices of יחזקאל *Yechezkel* we
learn that an אבל avel *avel* does the same. So obviously it's
all through a certain lens of interpretation of a sense already of
what it is that an אבל avel *avel* does. But anyway, God
says to יחזקאל *Yechezkel* do not go ahead and enveil your face,
so from there we can infer that a normal אבל avel *avel*
will enveil his face. מנודה Menudeh מהו בעטיפת הראש *Menudeh mahu b'atifat
harosh*, how about somebody in נידוי *nidui*? אמר רב יוסף תא שמע
Amar Rav Yosef tashma. *Amar Rav Yosef tashma*, ואין מתעטפין ויושבין כמנודין
וכאבלים *v'ein misatfin v'yoshvin k'menudin u'cha'avelim*. Remember the משנה Mishnah. *mishna* by
in תענית taanis. *Taanis*, when they weren't answered in the prayers after
a series of fasts, it says they wrap themselves around, you know,
they wrap their faces, and they sit like people that are in
that are ostracized and in mourning, עד שירחמו עליהן מן השמים *ad
sheyerachamu aleihen min hashamayim*, until God has compassion. So you see that
that's what a מנודה Menudeh *menudeh* does, wraps the face, covers the
face. אמר ליה אביי amar lei Abaye *Amar lei Abaye*, so אביי
*Abaye* responded, no, דילמא מנודה לשמים שאני dilma menudeh l'shamayim shani. דחמיר
d'chamir *lo, dilma menudeh l'shamayim shani d'chamir*. Now that's like מנודה menudeh,
לשמים *menudeh l'shamayim*, it's like God has ostracized them. So maybe that's
worse, but that doesn't prove that a normal person who is a
מנודה menudeh? *menudeh* would have to do the same practices. So we
don't have an exact answer by a מנודה menudeh *menudeh* about this.
מצורע metzora מהו בעטיפת הראש *Metzora mahu b'atifat harosh*? How about a
מצורע metzora, *metzora*, does he have to wrap his face? תא שמע
ta shma *Tashma*, come and hear, ועל שפם יעטה Ve'al safam ya'ateh,
*v'al safam ya'ateh*, that's by the מצורע metzora *metzora*, just like we
said almost word for word what the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* by יחזקאל
*Yechezkel* was. And the מצורע metzora *metzora* says it explicitly, right, cover
up the mouth,
so מכלל *michlal*, from here you can infer שחייב בעטיפת הראש *shechayav
b'atifat harosh*, he is obligated in wrapping the head. relegated, שמע מינה,
shma mina, that's a good proof. And let's be honest, the simple
sense of the משנה Mishnah. by the מנודה menudeh is the same.
And this makes sense, right, because these things about the clothing that
you wear, right, if you're covering over your face, it's means you're
not interacting directly with people. You're not sort of having that direct
face-to-face encounter, right, you're separating yourself, you're sealing yourself off from the
interpersonal and from society. And this is the way in which מנודה
menudeh and מצורע metzora. do share with אבילות, the sense of being
cut off from society. So although the גמרא Gemara says, well, maybe
you can't prove it by מנודה, menudeh the simple sense it's explicit
by מצורע metzora? and the simple sense of מנודה menudeh is that
way as well, that they do do this practice, because this does
reflect that element of what that identity of מנודה menudeh and מצורע.
Metzora Okay, so that so we've got bathing, I'm sorry, we've got
haircuts and עטיפת הראש, Atifat harosh, both of those let's note have
to do with appearance, and appearance like I said the sort of
anti-social appearance and so far the evidence is that that's all the
same by these three categories. Now let's do a third thing. אבל
אסור להניח תפילין. Avel assur lehaniach tfillin. An אבל avel is not
allowed to put on תפילין, Tfillin, מדקאמר ליה רחמנא ליחזקאל, Midka'amar lei
rachmana le'yechezkel, this is only the first day. The גמרא Gemara is
not always distinguishing first day, later days, אנינות, Aninus, אבילות, until. An
אבל avel cannot put on תפילין Tfillin first day, מדקאמר ליה רחמנא
ליחזקאל, Midka'amar lei rachmana le'yechezkel, because God says to יחזקאל, פארך חבוש
עליך, Pe'ercha chavosh alecha, your glory you should put on, you know,
you should put on yourself, you should don on yourself, and glory
he understood to be תפילין, Tfillin, and again understanding that יחזקאל's the
exception. מכלל דכולי עלמא אסור, Miklal dechulei alma assur, from here we
can infer that everybody else is forbidden because that's like a sense
of like glory, and in a state of glory is not appropriate
for an אבל. aveil So that's not exactly about being societally sort
of, you know, cut off. It's different, it's about an emotional state
of being, like a state of so that might not necessarily be
a problem for מנודה menudeh and מצורע, Metzora, and let's take a
look. So מנודה מהו בתפילין? Menudeh mai b'tfillin? תיקו. Teiku. What's the
law about a מנודה menudeh. and תפילין? Tfillin? We don't know, we
don't have any evidence one way or the other. מצורע מהו בתפילין?
Metzora mai b'tfillin? How about a מצורע? Metzora. תא שמע: ta shema.
והצרוע, Vehachatzarua, and the one with צרעת, לרבות כהן גדול. Lerabbot kohen
gadol. So that we said before, even a כהן גדול Kohen gadol
does the practices of a מצורע. Metzora בגדיו יהיו פרומים, Bgadav yihyu
frumim, the clothes are rent, שיהיו קרועים, Sheyihyu k'ru'im, that they should
be torn. Okay. וראשו יהיה פרוע, Parua the hair should grow wild.
אין פריעה אלא גידול שיער, Ein pri'ah ela gidul se'ar, it's the
growing of the hair which is not getting a haircut, which we
said before. דברי רבי אליעזר, Divrei Rabbi Eliezer, that's what Rabbi Eliezer
says. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, now Rabbi Akiva says, נאמר
הויה בראש ונאמר הויה בבגד. Ne'emar havayah b'rosh vene'emar havayah b'veged. It
says shall be by the head, ראשו יהיה פרוע, Rosho yihyeh parua,
and it says shall be by the garment, בגדיו יהיו פרומים. Bgadav
yihyu frumim. מה הויה האמורה בבגד, Ma havayah ha'amurah b'veged, the same
way the status of the clothes is דבר שחוץ מגופו, Davar shechootz
migufo, something outside of the body, the way he wears his clothes,
אף הויה בראש Af havayah b'rosh when it says your head shall
be פרוע Parua is דבר שחוץ מגופו, Davar shechootz migufo, something not
about the hair itself, but something that you would go out on
top of the hair or outside of the hair, but not the
hair itself. And that's what you don't do. So what's he talking
about? What so מאי לאו תפילין? Mai lav tfillin? It must mean
he means the hair is exposed because you're not wearing your תפילין.
Tfillin. So that's what he means, חוץ מגופו. Chootz migufo. Isn't that
that must be what רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva reading the פסוק Pasuk
to mean. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב פפא לא, Amar
rav papa lo, no, who says it's talking about תפילין? Tfillin? אקומסתא
וסודרא, Akumsa vesudra, it's talking about a hat and a scarf, you
know, a type of a a turban, talking about a normal hair
covering you would wear, right, like by the סוטה Sotah when it
says ופרע את ראש האשה, Ufarah et rosh ha'ishah, right, so that's
the question, uncover the hair or does it mean undo the hair
and let the hair grow wild? So פרוע is like wild hair,
but how is your hair wild? Is your hair wild because it's
not cut and it's not braided, or is it wild because it's
not covered? So the גמרא Gemara very reasonably understands that רבי עקיבא's
Rabbi Akiva not talking about תפילין, Tfillin, he means your head is
uncovered and therefore the hair is growing wild but it doesn't necessarily
mean not cutting. Now תוספות tosafos says of course רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva doesn't disagree with the idea that a מצורע Metzora is not
allowed to cut his hair, but רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva saying in
addition to not being allowed to cut your hair and having to
let it grow long, you're also not allowed to cover it, you
have to let it uncovered and that's similar to the garment aspect
of the rent clothes. Okay, so we do not have evidence that
a מנודה menudeh or מצורע Metzora is אסור בתפילין Assur b'tfillin and
logically, the reason we don't have evidence is logically they should be
מותר בתפילין. Mutar b'tfillin. תפילין Tfillin is not something that's about מנודה
menudeh and מצורע, metzora? right? תפילין Tfillin is about this sense of
like pride and glory. Now of course you could say, again, somebody
ostracized from society maybe shouldn't be feeling so great and have that
sense of like the glory of God's name on them, but nevertheless
it's not about the aspect of, you know, sort of cut off
from society. That's not what that practice is about. Whereas by אבילות,
a lot of practices are directly about reflective of the inner emotional
state. And therefore, that's why תפילין Tfillin is אסור Assur on the
first day, because the גמרא Gemara quotes another פסוק Pasuk, specifically on
the first day, אחריתה כיום מר, Acharisa k'yom mar, it's like a
real state of bitterness does not allow that sense of that glory
that comes from having God's name on you wearing the תפילין. Tfillin.
So that's אבילות. practices are both about society and about reflective of
one's inner state. The other practices are just about society and therefore
this thing like תפילין tfillin is there's no good reason they shouldn't
be doing it and there's no evidence that they don't do it.
Yes.
The beginning of אבילות the language is one of having a פטור
patur from מצוות mitzvos entire.
That's אוננות. oninus.
We're not doing
אוננות. oninus. Just... שפת אמת Sfas Emes asks does that language also
apply to the מנודה, menudeh in other words he's פטור patur from
תפילין? tfillin?
Yeah, I mean if he's not אסור assur he's חייב but the
whole issue of פטורים pturim by an אבל aveil and אוננות oninus
and we're although the גמרא Gemara mentioned אוננות oninus before let's just
bracket that. Okay, so now the גמרא continues. So we have that
same practices by haircut and and sort of you know cloaked face
but presumably different practices in terms of תפילין. tfillin. Okay now we
get onto the third
thing. אבל aveil אסור בשאלת שלום. assur b'shailas shalom. An אבל aveil
cannot you know ask about for people you know about people's welfare
and couldn't be asked about his welfare. Now we translate this as
not even saying like hello okay because שאלת שלום shailas shalom is
a form of greeting. But again in the גמרא it's much more
like how are you, how's everything doing, how's the wife, how's the
kids, you know it's asking after somebody's welfare. Okay and that obviously
is not appropriate for somebody who's not in a number one a
state of שלום shalom and again this sort of sense of being
more removed from society and from that type of social interaction. Okay
how do you know this? דקאמר ליה רחמנא ליחזקאל d'ka'amar lei rachmana
l'Yechezkel because God said to יחזקאל האנק דום, he'anek dom, be silent.
So interpreted in this context. מנודה מהו בשאלת שלום, menudeh mahu b'shailas
shalom, how about a מנודה? menudeh So logically based on what I've
been saying a מנודה menudeh should be אסור assur right, it's about
this whole social interaction. So let's take a look. אמר רב יוסף
תא שמע amar rav yosef ta shma. come and hear ובשאלת שלום
שבין אדם לחברו u'b'shailas shalom she'bein adam l'chavero
this thing that we the way the practice is of the in
מסכת תענית Masechet Taanis after they haven't been answered after the first
few fasts right they start doing more severe practices. And one of
the things they're not allowed to do is שאלת שלום shailas shalom
inquiring after one another's welfare. And the משנה and the and the
משנה says שאלת שלום shailas shalom they're forbidden in שאלת שלום shailas
shalom שבין אדם לחברו she'bein adam l'chavero one person to his friend
כבני אדם הנזופים למקום kivnei adam hanizufim l'makom like people that are
sort of rejected by by God. So you see that they're אסור
assur in שאלת שלום. shailas shalom. מנודין, menudin,
נזופים nizufim is seen as the same as מנודין menudin like they've
been ostracized and cast away. So that's a pretty good proof that
that's a state of נידוי. אמר ליה אביי no דילמא מנודה menudah
לשמים שאני. אביי says what he said before. You can't bring evidence
from a case when they are being rejected by God. That might
be worse, דחמיר it's more weighty. Okay so it's not an absolute
proof but the simple sense is that a מנודה menudah is forbidden.
מצורע מהו בשאלת שלום, metzora mahu b'shailas shalom, how about a מצורע?
metzora? תא שמע Ta shema. ועל שפה יעטה v'al safah ya'ateh on
the lips shall cover over what we said before about cloaking the
face שיהו שפתותיו דבוקות זו בזו she'yehu sfosov dvukos zu b'zu that
his lips should be like closed one to the next should be
stuck to one another שיהא כמנודה וכאבל ואסור בשאלת שלום. she'yehei k'menudeh
u'k'avel v'assur b'shailas shalom. He should be like a מנודה menudah and
an אבל aval, and you know
and he's forbidden in in inquiring after his welfare and inquiring after
other people's welfare. So you see explicitly
that a that a מצורע metzora is forbidden in שאלת שלום. shailas
shalom. שמע מינה, shma mina. that's a good proof. So then the
גמרא says one minute it also mentioned מנודה menudah there. ונפשוט מיניה
למנודה, v'nifshot minei l'menudeh, why not also learn that a מנודה menudah
can't do שאלת שלום? shailas shalom? Because it said this מצורע his
lips have to be stuck to one another like a מנודה menudah,
and an אבל aveil. and is forbidden in שאלת שלום. shailas shalom.
So let's learn out that a מנודה menudah? is also forbidden. So
the גמרא says אמר רב אחא בר פנחס משמיה דרב יוסף amar
Rav Acha bar Pinchas mishmei d'Rav Yosef מי קתני שאסור? mi katani
she'assur? It doesn't say he is forbidden in שאלת שלום shailas shalom
like a מנודה. menudah, It says שיהא כמנודה וכאבל, she'yehei k'menudeh u'k'avel,
he's number one he's like a מנודה menudah and an אבל avel
קתני. katani. במילי אחרנייתא b'millei achranyasa maybe in other ways he's like
a מנודה menuda and an אבל avel like we said before you
know he lets his hair grow wild he doesn't do laundry ואסור
נמי בשאלת שלום v'assur nami b'shailas shalom and he's forbidden in שאלת
שלום. shailas shalom. So it's pretty funny right? So the phrase is
it says right שפתותיו sfosov שפתותיו sfosov
דבוקות dvukos right
זו בזו zu b'zu right שיהא she'yehei כמנודה וכאבל k'menudeh u'k'avel or
is
it אבל ומנודה? avel u'menudeh? מנודה
וכאבל menudeh
u'k'avel ואסור בשאלת שלום.
v'assur b'shailas shalom. So what we're saying is right these things like
they're all saying the same thing מנודה menuda and אבל avel. which
who are אסור assur in שאלת שלום. shailas shalom. But it's saying
no keep silent אסור בשאלת שלום assur b'shailas shalom and by the
way you're also like an אבל avel, and a מנודה menuda for
other things like for doing your laundry. So it's a very hard
read of that ברייתא braisa right to say that this is saying
a different point from the first and the last part of the
phrase right? Keep the lips stuck together don't do שאלת שלום shailas
shalom you're like a מנודה menuda, and an אבל avel for other
things. Doesn't sound like it. It sounds like it... It’s all saying
the same thing. But anyway, the point is the simple sense of
this is that it’s clear that a מצורע cannot do שאילת שלום,
sheilas sholom, and certainly the פשט pshat of everything is that a
מנודה menuda? cannot do שאילת שלום. sheilas sholom. And again, that stands
to reason, because this is about the social interaction, okay? So we’ve
got that what are the things that nobody can do? The haircut,
the haircut, the wrapping of the face has to be done, the
איסור issur שאילת שלום, sheilas sholom, that seems all of that is
societal that nobody can do. The thing that the אבל avel is
singled out for so far is different from them is the איסור
issur of wearing תפילין. tefillin. That’s not about these societal aspects. Okay,
so now we
continue.
Right, שאילת שלום sheilas sholom you do on
חול המועד.
chol ha-moed. Most of the other than the haircut and the laundry,
all these things you do on חול המועד. תפילין tefillin is a
big מחלוקת, machlokes, but yes, for very different reasons. But that’s actually
fascinating to note, yet another thing might be for a different reason
that might have a parallel with the תפילין tefillin depending on how
you פסקן pasken about תפילין tefillin on חול המועד. But yeah, but
we’ll keep all these lists that will be other than the haircut
and the laundry will obviously be things you do on חול המועד.
Okay, so now we’ve done שאילת שלום. sheilas sholom. Now we’re going
to go to another thing.
אבל Avel, אסור בדברי תורה. assur b'divrei Torah. Now an אבל Avel
can’t learn תורה. Torah. So what do you think before we go
any further? What do you think about it based on the framework
I’ve been setting up? מנודה Menudeh and a מצורע. Yes for תורה
Torah or no? What would you say? Yes! What does that have
to do with societal interaction? But if תורה Torah is like we
learned like תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av, right? You know, words of God
משמחי לב, mesamchei lev, right? If תורה Torah is about שמחה Simcha
and also תורה Torah you know also gets to the whole idea
of אנינות aninus and it’s about an affirmation of the meaning of
life and so on, you know, which is part of why they
say like an אונן onen is אסור במצווה. assur b'mitzvah. But anyway,
those are issues which are contrary to the state of אבילות, right?
Whereas
why should a מצורע and a מנודה Menudeh. be אסור assur in
תורה? Torah?
Because a מנודה Menudeh is somebody who the רבנן Rabbanan are saying
we do not allow you to participate in the norms of our
society until you conform.
Oh, so he might not be able to go to a שיעור
shiur or teach a שיעור, shiur, but can he open up a
גמרא and a חומש Chumash and learn on his own? Why not?
Right? So again, מנודה Menudeh is about societal aspects. Is he rejecting
the תורה? Torah?
Yeah, but you know the question is that we can sort of
say the specific state of נידוי is to act in a way
of ostracization and this is not something that’s an expression of ostracization.
So let’s take a look. מנודה, menudeh? okay, so אבל Avel, אסור
בדברי תורה. assur b'divrei Torah. רחמנא ליחזקאל, be silent. And now we’re
reading silent not to be שאילת שלום sheilas sholom but תורה. Torah.
מנודה מהו בדברי תורה? menudah mahu b'divrei Torah? What about a מנודה?
menudeh אמר רב יוסף תא שמע. amar rav yosef ta shma. מנודה,
menudeh we have a ברייתא. braisa Somebody who’s in נידוי, שונה ושונין
לו. shoneh v'shonin lo.
Look at this. You’re even allowed to, he’s even allowed to give
a שיעור shiur and he can go to a שיעור. shiur. נשכר
ונשכרין לו. niscar v'niscarin lo. He can hire himself out for labor
and he can hire laborers. So that’s why he’s not like excommunicated,
right? It’s not as harsh. He’s not completely cut off. He does
certain practices that naturally sort of set him apart, but it’s not
like there’s no intercourse with him, there’s absolutely no interaction with him.
No, you’re allowed to teach him, he can go to a שיעור,
shiur, he’s allowed to hire people, he’s allowed to rent himself out,
hire himself out. מוחרם, muchram, however, חרם, somebody who’s excommunicated, לא שונה
ולא שונין לו. lo shoneh v'lo shonin lo. Doesn’t teach others and
you don’t teach him. לא נשכר ולא נשכרין לו. lo niscar v'lo
niscarin lo. Doesn’t rent himself out and doesn’t rent out laborers. So
that, a מוחרם muchram is completely sort of excommunicated. This person, he
does practices, but you’re not forbidden to have interactions with them, right?
You maybe don’t do שאילת שלום, sheilas sholom, but it doesn’t mean
you can’t talk to him. אבל, Avel. but even a מוחרם, muchram,
שונה הוא לעצמו. shoneh hu l'atzmo. He can learn his own תורה.
Torah. שלא יפסוק לימודו, shelo yifosek limudo, he doesn’t have to stop
learning תורה Torah for himself. Maybe he doesn’t do it with other
people. So even a מוחרם muchram is allowed to learn תורה. Torah.
Different than an אבל. Avel ועושה לו חנות קטנה בשביל פרנסתו. v'oseh
lo chanut ktana bishvil parnasato. And even a מוחרם muchram can have
himself a tiny little store, you know, do a little business in
order to put food on the table, which is
fascinating. ואמר רב זביד ואמר רב, V'amar Rav Zevid v'amar Rav, זבוני
מיא בפיקסא דארבות. zvuni maya b'piksa d'Arvos. He could sell water in
this
place, the פיקסא דארבות, piksa d'Arvos, which the רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel
says is like somewhere out in the middle of nowhere. So on
the one hand it’s like people need water because it’s out in
the middle of the desert, but also it’s a type of a
business that’s not about
societal interaction. שמע מינה. shema mina. So you see that a מנודה
menudeh can learn תורה. Torah. מצורע מהו בדברי תורה? metzora mahu b'divrei
Torah? How about a מצורע? Can he learn תורה? Torah? תא שמע
והודעתם לבניך ולבני בניך יום אשר עמדת לפני ה׳ אלוקיך בחורב. Tashma,
v'hodatam l'vanecha v'livnei vanecha yom asher amadta lifnei Hashem Elokecha b'Chorev. You
shall refer, tell your children the day you stood before God in
חורב. Chorev. מה להלן באימה וביראה וברתת ובזיע. mah lehalan b'eima u'v'yira
u'v'reses u'v'zeia. The same way at that time when at Mount Sinai
it was with fear and awe and trembling and sweat, מכאן אמרו
mikan amru so therefore when you learn תורה Torah even in the
future you have to be in a similar state of mind. מכאן
אמרו. Mi-kan amru. From here they said, on the one hand הזבים
והמצורעים והבאים על הנידות מותרין לקרות בתורה בנביאים ובכתובים. Ha-zavim ve-ha-metzora'im ve-ha-ba'im
al ha-niddot mutarin likrot ba-Torah bi-Nevi'im u-bi-Khtuvim. People that are just טמא
even if their טומאה is because of something that's directly about their
body, like they've had various flows, a זב zav or מצורע, right?
So there's your מצורע case, or men who has had sex with
a נדה. niddah. Interesting, it doesn't mention נידות niddot because it's assuming
men, although there is a, if I remember correctly, there is a
ברייתא that does mention נידות, niddot, but this only mentions בעלי נידות.
ba'alei niddot. All these people מותרין לקרות בתורה בנביאים ובכתובים mutarin likrot
ba-Torah bi-Nevi'im u-bi-Khtuvim can learn Torah just because they're טמא. Who cares?
טומאה is not about the
proper improper state of mind, it's just about a הלכה'דיק halachic status.
ולשנות במדרש ובשס ובהלכות ובאגדות Ve-lishnot be-Midrash u-be-Shas u-be-Halachot u-be-Aggadot and they
can learn מדרש Midrash and, you know, and גמרא and הלכות and
the whole thing and משנה. But ובעל קריין אסורין, u-ba'al keryan asurin,
but a בעל קרי, ba'al keri, somebody who's had a seminal emission,
that reflects a, although you could say it was in the past,
but nevertheless until you've moved into a new state by going to
the מקוה, mikvah, reflects a less sort of serious state of mind,
something that's, you know, much more sort of connected to what I'd
say physical sort of pleasure and therefore should not in that state
of mind be learning Torah. So anyway, and that's a practice, that's
a whole discussion in ברכות Berachot where they had these practices about
a בעל קרי ba'al keri not דאוונעןing davening and not saying ברכות
berachos and not learning Torah, and most of that stuff was basically
overridden. But that's another conversation. What we see is that a מצורע
is allowed to learn Torah. So the גמרא says שמע מינה. Shema
mina. So again, what can a מצורע do and a מנודה menudeh
do that an אבל Avel cannot? Learn Torah and wear תפילין. tefillin.
Those are things that are about their sort of emotional state of
being, about sadness, about mourning and so on, which are they're sort
of, you know, they're seen to be running up against in terms
of these practices, but it's not about the aspects of מנודה menudeh
and מצורע which are about expressions of this more societal ostracization. Okay,
so now we continue. So we have the areas of similarity and
these areas of difference. Fifth thing, I'm losing
track. אבל אסור בתכבוסת. Avel assur be-tichboset. An אבל Avel's cannot do
laundry, דכתיב וישלח יואב תקועה ויקח משם אשה חכמה ויאמר אליה התאבלי
נא ולבשי נא בגדי אבל ואל תסוכי שמן. de-chtiv Vayishlach Yoav Tekoa
vayikach misham isha chachama vayomer eleiha hit’abli na u-livshi na bigdei eivel
ve-al tasuchi shemen. So this is the whole sort of scheme that
יואב Yoav had. He took this woman and he said, you know,
act as if you're mourning, wear garments of אבילות and do not
anoint yourself with oil. והיית כאישה זה ימים רבים מתאבלת על מת.
Ve-hayit ke-isha zeh yamim rabbim mit’abelet al meit. Okay, and you'll be
like a woman who has been mourning over the dead for many
days. So whatever that story is, anyway, one of the things that
we see is בגדי bigdei אבילות. So rather than saying it means
wearing black clothes, right, we understand בגדי bigdei אבילות means unlaundered garments.
Alright, so
that's
an אבל. Avel's מנודין ומצורעין מה הן בתכבוסת? Menudin u-metzorain ma hen
be-tichboset? How about מנודין menudin and מצורעין? metzorain? So we already know
the answer because we learned it from our משנה. They're allowed, if
they, you know, if their status changes on יום טוב, Yom Tov.
they're allowed to do their laundry because they weren't allowed to do
their laundry when they were in that status. So the גמרא says
תא שמע. ta shma. מנודין ומצורעין אסור לספר ולכבס. Menudin u-metzorain assur
lesaper u-lekhabes. We had the ברייתא at the top of the דף
that said that they cannot do laundry and get a haircut. שמע
מינה. Shma mina. So we don't have a source for it, but
again, by the מצורע, and we have a ברייתא, we don't have
a biblical source, but by the מצורע the תורה Torah says right,
בגדיו יהיו פרומים, begadav yihyu ferumim, let the garments are rent, so
clearly there's a sense of garments that are expressing this state and
therefore, the same way there're garments of אבילות, there're garments of מנודה
menudeh and מצורע which is understood to be unlaundered. And again, this
is part of that sense of separate from society. So you have
the garments and the haircut, that's the same, and the wrapping around
of the face and the שאילת שלום. she’ilat shalom. That's all the
same. That's אבל, Avel, מנודה, menudeh מצורע. And you can see how
all of those are societally related, right? And then we have just
אבל Avel and none of the others so far is Torah and
תפילין. tefillin. Okay, let's keep on going. אבל חייב בקריעה. Avel chayav
bi-kri'ah. An אבל avel has to rent the garment, דקאמר ליה רחמנא
לבני אהרן לא תפרומו, de-ka'amar lei Rachmana li-vnei Aharon lo tifromu, do
not rent your garments. וכל דכולי עלמא מחייב, Ve-chol
de-kulei alma mechayev, everybody
else is obligated. מנודה מהו בקריעה? Menuda mahu bi-kri'ah? תיקו. Teiku. What
about a מנודה? menudeh We don't know. We don't have any evidence.
מצורע מהו בקריעה? Metzora mahu bi-kri'ah? How about a מצורע? תא שמע.
בגדיו יהיו פרומים, Bgadav yihyu frumim, the clothes will be rent, שיהיו
מקורעים, Sheyihyu mikurai'im, that they should be rent garments. שמע מינה. shma
minah. So now this is fascinating because this, on the one hand
you could say, it's similar to the whole idea of the garments,
right? So here we have rent garments. Okay. And that's, you know,
that's implicit in the פסוק, right, by the מצורע at least, right?
This is ראשו יהיה פרוע, Rosho yihyeh parua, ראשו יהיה פרוע, and
this is בגדיו יהיו פרומים, Bgadav yihyu frumim, בגדיו יהיו פרומים, Bgadav
yihyu frumim, ועל שפם יעטה, Ve'al safam ya'ateh, ועל שפם יעטה, Ve'al
safam ya'ateh, right? And these other two, שאלת שלום She'elat shalom is
obviously related to ועל שפם יעטה,
ובגדיו יהיו פרומים U'vgadav yihyu frumim
is to the laundered garments. So basically all these are פסוקים Pesukim
by the מצורע, right? So far these are just more or less
elaborations of the פסוקים by the מצורע. Okay, but anyway, there's a
difference here about saying rent garments by the מצורע and what we
normally talk about about an אבל, avel because by an אבל avel
it's about wearing rent
garments, but it's also about something else. What is it also about?
Doing the act of קריאה, Kriyah, right? The act of קריאה Kriyah
is an act of expression of mourning, of loss, of
being sort
of shattered, right? And so therefore that's an interesting question. We never
say that a מנודה menudeh? or מצורע has to do an act
of קריאה. Kriyah. Could they get somebody else to rent their garments
for them? Presumably yes, right? It's about wearing rent garments but not
necessarily about an act of קריאה. Kriyah. So although the גמרא doesn't
say this, I would argue that the act of קריאה Kriyah is
unique to an אבל, avel but it's wearing rent garments which is
in this category. Okay. Yes. The onset of the מועד Moed ends
the אבלות Avelus. for the אבל. avel Yep. It doesn't end the
state of being a מנודה. menudeh Right. And that's exactly why. Because
I said this is about, this is about אבלות Avelus, and שמחה
Simcha, are in opposition. This is about societal sort of ostracization, which
although that gets in the way of שמחה, Simcha is not seen
as שמחה Simcha is directly attacking it. So my question is, does
that imply ironically that the מנודה menudeh and the מצורע during חול
המועד continue not being able to do the things that they can't,
whereas the אבל avel can? Right. Because the אבל avel, also because,
it's a good point which maybe I should even say a little
bit sharper, the אבל avel sense of separation from society is rooted
in the אבל avel emotional state. So whereas an אבל, avel whereas
these is, so when the שמחה Simcha, directly addresses the emotional state,
it has implications for all the practices of the אבלות. aveilus Whereas
this is only about the societal practice and therefore שמחה, simcha because
I have a מצות שמחה Mitzvat Simcha that doesn't directly speak to
these types of, so that's the way I understand it. The onset
of אבלות, aveilus the onset of יום טוב is before, is quite
before יום טוב, the haircut for יום טוב. And the מנודה menudeh
will be walking around. Exactly. Everyone else will be... Exactly. Okay. So
now the גמרא continues. Okay. אבל חייב בכפיית המיטה. Avel chayav bichfiyat
hamitah. An אבל avel has to turn the beds upside down. We
don't do this nowadays, we cover the mirrors instead. Okay. דתני בר
קפרא. Detani Bar Kappara. בר קפרא Bar Kappara taught: דמות דיוקני נתתי
בהן. Demut diyukni natati bahen. I have given my image to them,
says God, the divine image, צלם אלוקים. Tzelem Elokim. Anybody know where
the word, what the word דיוקני Diyukni comes from? Greek? Greek for
icon. Yeah, icon, דיוקני. Diyukni. Okay, so my icon, my image I
have given to them, you know, the divine image. ובעוונותיהם, U've'avonoteihem, in
their sins, הפכתיה. Hafachtiha. So I have been forced to turn it
upside down. So it's a loss of the divine image and somehow
I never really fully understand that.
But some sense about things are turned upside down as a result
of the death and it's a terrible loss and tragedy, so the
beds are turned upside down. The reason we translate it into practice
of the covering of the mirrors, I think, is this idea of
like, you know, the again, the sort of seeing of the human
image and of the face and whatever in some sense that some
of that, you know, some humanity was lost. So that's the practice.
כפו מיטותיהם עליה. Kafu mitoteihem aleha. Interesting that the death was a
result of sin. Yeah well that's also interesting, because now we're supposed
to interpret every death as the basis of sin, you know, and
there's other גמרות Gemarot that speak about sort of doing ניחום אבלים
Nichum Aveilim and so on and, you know, is that what you
say, "Oh, don't worry, it happened because of sin"? Right, so it's
wonderful, you know, that's like the גמרא says that's איסור אונאת דברים,
Issur ona'at devarim, it's what איוב Iyov's friends... Oh, you mean בעוונותיהם
ba-avonoteihem the generic sins. That's also a good point. Here's a translation
of צלם, tzelem, with the צלם. tzelem. Well, yeah, it's icon though.
Right. Okay, so the גמרא says מנודה ומצורע מהן בכפיית המטה? menudeh
u-metzora mahen bi-kefiyas ha-mittah? תיקו. teiku. But all תיקו teiku means at
this stage is we don't have any evidence one way or the
other. But I'm reading the תיקו teiku basically as if there's no
evidence, you don't do it. And here clearly, you know, כפיית המטה
kefiyas ha-mittah is something that as we just learned from this ברייתא
is very is very distinctive to אבלות aveilus. and about what אבלות
is about. אבל אסור בעשיית מלאכה. avel assur ba-asiyas melacha. An אבל
avel, cannot do מלאכה, melacha. cannot go out to his job and
so on. דכתיב והפכתי חגיכם לאבל. di-ksiv ve-hafachati chageichem le-avel. I will
turn your your holidays into mourning. מה חג אסור בעשיית מלאכה אף
אבל אסור בעשיית מלאכה. mah chag assur ba-asiyas melacha af avel assur
ba-asiyas melacha. The same way you don't do מלאכה melacha. on a
חג, chag, an אבל does not do מלאכה. melacha מנודה מהו בעשיית
מלאכה? menudeh mahu ba-asiyas melacha? How about a מנודה? menudeh אמר רב
יוסף amar Rav Yosef תא שמע. וכשהאמרו אסור בעשיית מלאכה לא אמרו
אלא ביום אבל בלילה מותר. u-k-she-omru assur ba-asiyas melacha lo omru ela
ba-yom aval ba-laylah muttar. This is again by the people that are
observing a תענית. taanis. And when the תעניות taaniyos became more severe,
it says one of the things they can't do is they can't
do מלאכה. melacha. But that's only in the daytime, in night it's
allowed. וכן אתה מוצא במנודה ובאבל. ve-chein attah motzei bi-menudeh u-va-avel. And
the same you find by מנודה menuda and an אבל that they
can't presumably meaning that they can't do מלאכה. melacha So מאי לאו
אכולהו? mai lav a-kuleihu? Doesn't it mean like all of this, like
מנודה menuda and אבל are אסור assur in מלאכה melacha just like
we've just been discussing? לא אשארא. lo a-she'ara. No, like we sort
of got out of it before. These people are like מנודה and
אבלים aveilim for other practices, not necessarily making the comparison about the
מלאכה. So the simple sense is is that a מנודה is אסור
בעשיית מלאכה assur ba-asiyas melacha but it's not explicit. Okay. תא שמע.
So now we're going to try again. מנודה שונה ושונה לו נשכר
ונשכר לו. menudeh shoneh ve-shoneh lo niskar ve-niskar lo. We have an
explicit ברייתא that actually says it's allowed. It says a מנודה can
be hired out to work. שמע מינה. So that is a good
proof. So now we find out that a מנודה is מותר בעשיית
מלאכה. muttar ba-asiyas melacha. מצורע מהו בעשיית מלאכה? metzora mahu ba-asiyas melacha?
How about a מצורע? תיקו. teiku. We don't have any evidence. So
again, lack of evidence in this context presumably means that it's מותר.
muttar. So interesting, and this would have been one thing you might
wanted to have put in that category but we don't, is עשיית
מלאכה. asiyas melacha. Because עשיית מלאכה asiyas melacha on the one hand
is a social type of an activity, right, you know you're out
there engaged in society and so on. But we just learned, you
know, that a מנודה is not like a מוחרם. muchram. A מנודה
is somebody that you can hire and be hired to and you
know, and can go to a שיעור shiur and teach a שיעור
shiur and so on. Not completely ostracized from society, just practices that
set them apart, but not actually cutting off all interactions with society.
So עשיית מלאכה asiyas melacha is okay. The עשיית מלאכה asiyas melacha
of an אבל is normally identified not because of to take you
out of society, but it's normally identified as the reason an אבל
doesn't do מלאכה is because it will distract the person from the
אבלות. So normally the reason given for the איסור issur of עשיית
מלאכה asiyas melacha is specific to that emotional state of the אבל,
of the issue of, you know, it's מסיח דעת מן האבלות masiach
daas min ha-aveilus is normally the explanation given. So although this is
an interesting one as I said though, because this is one you
could have theoretically imagined is very much about being part or not
part of society, but again, it's not as severe in this case,
and here it's presumably about something else. Is מלאכה here the technical
term... no, ל"ט מלאכות? No. I mean, you know, we have a
hard enough time figuring out what that means in the חול המועד
context and as almost תוספות aside, it's hard to imagine that's what
it means here by חול המועד. But here it's much more about
engaged in the normal type of professional activity. Let's just read one
more. אבל אסור ברחיצה, avel assur bi-rechitza, דכתיב di-ksiv an אבל can't
bathe. דכתיב ואל תסוכי שמן. di-ksiv ve-al tasuchi shemen. Do not anoint
yourself by the case by יואב. Yoav. ורחיצה בכלל סיכה. ve-rechitza bi-khlal
sikah. And bathing is in the same category as anointing. Okay,
so taking care of your physical body. מנודה מהו ברחיצה? menudeh mahu
bi-rechitza? What about a מנודה? אמר רב יוסף תא שמע. כשאמרו אסור
ברחיצה, k-she-omru assur bi-rechitza, when they said by תענית ציבור taanis tzibur
that you can't bathe. לא אמרו אלא כל גופו. lo omru ela
kol gufo. That's only your whole body. אבל פניו ידיו ורגליו מותר.
aval panav yadav ve-raglav muttar. But the face and hands you can.
This is by a תענית. taanis וכן אתה מוצא במנודה ובאבל. ve-chein
attah motzei bi-menudeh u-va-avel. And same by מנודה and an אבל
presumably meaning that
they're forbidden in bathing with these with these allowances. So the גמרא
says מאי לאו אכולהו? mai lav a-kuleihu? Again, the simple sense is
that it's comparing מנודה and אבל to practices of bathing. לא אשארא.
lo a-she'ara. No, maybe it's comparing the practices of people in a
תענית to מנודה and אבל for other practices of מנודה and אבל,
not the one we're immediately talking about which is bathing, which is
again a hard read. The simple sense is that they cannot do
these actual forms. מצורע מהו ברחיצה? metzora mahu bi-rechitza? תיקו. teiku. What
about a מצורע? We don't know. So this is one where the
evidence is not so clear about bathing. And you know, and again,
it's like it is does raise an interesting question. Way that I
set it up, because it is true if somebody doesn't bathe they're
smelly and they'll be a little bit more on the outskirts of
society, but things are much more visible, right? Whereas bathing is, you
know, again, I mean it's true if you're walking around like who
was that guy in Peanuts, the guy always with the dust? Pig-Pen.
Pig-Pen, right? So okay, then that's true but if it's not at
that stage then bathing might be less and if you're not visibly
smelly might be less about this and more just about taking care
of your own like, you know, sort of, physical needs and focusing
on yourself and, you know, again, not exactly though it's not exactly
clear how that's like a שמחה unless the point is that by
not bathing you're more in a state of צער. tza'ar.
That's that idea.
Exactly, I thought that—oh, you mean like there was thieves in the
bathhouses. In the bathhouses.
Not so private. Right.
That's true. Yeah. So I do have to say the גמרא does
not come to a clear position by רחיצה rechitza and this is
interesting. I would more, I admit, I would more be inclined I
admit to put it in this category, but there's not evidence by
מצורע the evidence is not clear, by מנודה the simple sense is
that a מנודה is אסור assur ברחיצה be-rechitza but the גמרא sort
of equivocates. So we'll pick up with this tomorrow, okay? We'll put
רחיצה rechitza here as a question mark. Okay, so to be continued
tomorrow.
Americans bathe more than any people at any point in the history
of the planet.
Really? Well that's because we have running water.